Inventory of the Herbert H. Bateman Papers, 1946-1982, 1968-1982
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Public Employees-Collective Bargaining, 1970-1979. (Box-folder 14:4-11)
  - Background materials on public employees collective bargaining, 1976-1977., 10 items. (Box-folder 14:10)
    Including copies of August 1976 issue of State Government, Public Service Research Council booklet, Public Sector Bargaining, and Strikes, Summer 1977 issue of State Government, and transcripts of speeches by Governor Mills Godwin.
  - Background materials and correspondence relating to public employee (especially teachers) collective bargaining, 1977-1979, n.d., 45 items. (Box-folder 14:11)
    Including copy of October 1977 issue of State Government News, booklets by Virginia Education Association, letters opposing collective bargaining from national Right to Work Committee and the Virginia Manufacturers Association, constituent letters with Bateman's (form letter) relies, and undated copy of Bateman's form letter reply.
  Series 157: Radioactive Materials
- Correspondence, legislative materials, and reports relating to transportation of radioactive materials, 1977-1980., 31 items. (Box-folder 14:12)
  Especially materials relating to Virginia H.R. 1918, 1978-1979. File includes Nuclear Regulatory Commission Regulations, Virginia report of joint subcommittee studying the licensing of nuclear generating facilities, bills, amendments, substitutes, fact sheets, and testimony related to H.R. 1918, and 1980 report of Virginia Solid Waste Commission on low-level radioactive waste disposal.
  Series 158: Reapportionment
- Reapportionment, 1970-1981. (Box-folder 14:13-17)
  - Documents, statistics, and legislative papers relating to reapportionment of representative districts after 1970 census, 1970-1971., 21 items. (Box-folder 14:13)
    Including court decisions, findings of Reapportionment Study Commission, district maps, and Bateman's 1 February 1971 memo regarding reapportionment plan for Newport News.
    See also medium oversize and oversize, series 249.
  - Reports and other materials relating to reapportionment after 1970 census, 1970-1973, 12 items. (not including maps). (Box-folder 14:14)
    Including two reports by Attorney General on effects of judicial decisions on congressional and state reapportionment, brief by state Senators Henry Howell and Peter Babalas challenging constitutionality of reapportionment for City of Norfolk, "Population Panotama" of Newport News, Council of State Governments booklet, Reapportionment in the Seventies, 1973 court decision in case of City of Virginia Beach v. Henry E. Howell, Jr., et. al.
    See also maps in oversize file, series 249.
  - Memoranda and census figures relating to reapportionment after 1980 census, 1979-1980., 23 items. (Box-folder 14:15)
    Including packet of photocopies of news releases and clippings concerning effects of 1980 elections on reapportionment and housing issues, several copies of census figures and senatorial districts sent by Senator Hunter Andrews.
  - Documents relating to reapportionment after 1980 election, 1980-1981., 26 items. (Box-folder 14:16)
    Including bills and court decisions regarding Virginia's reapportionment plan, proposed new House of Delegates districts, and proposed amendments for redistricting in Portsmouth, Norfolk, and Hampton.
  - Court cases and documents from challenges to proposed reapportionment, August 1981, and December 1981 amended draft of reapportionment bill (H.R. 13), 1981., 6 items. (Box-folder 14:17)
  Series 159: Recommendations
- Recommendations, 1972-1982. (Box-folder 14:18-23)
  - Letters of recommendation, which Bateman wrote for constituents applying to law schools and for state jobs, with resumes, application and responses, 1972-1974., 83 items. (Box-folder 14:18)
  - Letters of recommendation, resumes, and responses of applicants for colleges, law schools, and state jobs, 1975-1982., 80 items. (Box-folder 14:19)
  - Letters of recommendation from Bateman for applicants to law schools and military academies, correspondence and resumes from applicants and responses from schools, 1979-1981., 87 items. (Box-folder 14:20)
  - Letters of recommendation for applicants to state law schools and military academies and related materials, 1981-1982., 64 items. (Box-folder 14:21)
  - Correspondence and other materials relating to job openings in state government, 1981-1982., 16 items. (Box-folder 14:22)
    Including appointment-vacancy lists, for 1982, solicitations in the administration of Governor-elect Charles Robb, and Bateman's correspondence with Robb regarding nominees.
  - Correspondence, resumes and other materials regarding Bateman's support of applicants for federal jobs., 34 items. (Box-folder 14:23)
  Series 160: Rehabilitation and Social Services
- Rehabilitation and Social Services, 1980-1981. (Box-folder 15:1-3)
  - Resolutions and newsletters from Virginia Association of the Deaf, King's Daughters Children's Hospital, and other agencies regarding rehabilitative services for children and the mentally retarded, 1980-1981., 13 items. (Box-folder 15:1)
  - Correspondence, memoranda and reports relating to work of Senate Committee on Rehabilitation and Social Services, 1980., 15 items. (Box-folder 15:2)
    Including information on parole and prison population and October 1980 report by the Association for Retarded Citizens.
  - Reports and memoranda relating to rehabilitation and social services in Virginia, 1981., 6 items. (Box-folder 15:3)
    Including JLARC report and "Action Agenda" on Title XX in Virginia and commentaries on "Action Agenda" and report of the Virginia Health Services Cost Review Commission.
  Series 161: Republican Caucus
- Memoranda, correspondence, and bulletins relating to activities of state Republican caucus, including several issues of the "Hot Line," January-March 1982., 12 items. (Box-folder 15:4)
  Series 162: Retirement
- Retirement, 1977-1981. (Box-folder 15:5-8)
  - Materials relating to Virginia Supplemental Retirement System (VSRS), 1977., 7 items. (Box-folder 15:5)
    Including report on audit for period 1 July 1972-30 June 1977.
    See also Public Employees, series 155-156.
  - Correspondence, addresses and reports pertaining to Virginia's Supplemental Retirement System (VSRS), 1978., 19 items. (Box-folder 15:6)
    Including documents on Bateman's personal benefits, booklets for members, booklet, "A Legislator's Guide to Public Pensions," and October 1978 JLARC report on the VSRS.
  - Reports on Virginia Retirement System, 1978-1980., 5 items. (Box-folder 15:7)
    Including 1979 and 1980 reports of the Virginia Retirement Study Commission.
  - Documents and correspondence relating to taxation of retirement income, 1980-1981., 19 items. (Box-folder 15:8)
    Especially reports to and minutes of meetings of state Senate Finance Committee.
  Series 163: Richmond Waterfront Terminals
- Photocopies of ordinances and correspondence, regarding Richmond waterfront terminals, and Bateman's handwritten notes concerning those documents, 1956-1958., 11 items. (Box-folder 15:9)
  Series 164: Right to Work Law
- Transcript of June 1980 debate, Right to Work: What Does it Really Mean? and letters received from constituents with some carbon copies of form letter reply, 1980., 35 items. (Box-folder 15:10)
  Series 165: Sales Tax on Vending machines
- Bill to reenact sales tax on vending machine operators, 1982., 2 items. Copies. (Box-folder 15:11)
  See also Vending Machine Taxes, series 210
  Series 166: Sales Tax Regulations
- Copy of Virginia retail sales and use tax regulations to take effect, 1 July 1982., 1 item. (Box-folder 15:12)
  Series 167: Savings and Loan Legislation
- Information on 1981 H.R. 1740, and copies of several 1982 House bills affecting savings and loans, 1981-1982., 13 items. (Box-folder 15:13)
  Series 168: School Distribution Formula
- School Distribution Formula, 1969-1971. (Box-folder 15:14-17)
  - Reports and memoranda relating to work of commission to study the formula for state aid to public schools and subcommittee to study constitutional implications of the commission, 1969., 11 items. (Box-folder 15:14)
    File contains minutes of meetings, committee and commission membership lists, interim report of study commission, report of subcommittee (which Bateman chaired) and proposed constitutional revisions.
  - Papers relating to work of commission studying school fund distribution formula on 1969, 1961-1969., 13 items. (Box-folder 15:15)
    Including distribution figures for 1961 and 1968-1969, report on North Carolina schools, copy of Bateman's 6 December 1969 address and draft of commission report, with statistics and Bateman's concurring opinion.
  - Material relating to work of commission to study public school fund distribution formula, 1970-1971., 20 items. (Box-folder 15:16)
    Including copy of commission report, packet of statistical tables, and Bateman's correspondence pertaining to formula and Newport News Public Schools.
    See also Newport News Public Education, series 124.
  - Undated report, The Distribution of State School Funds in Terms of Need, Ability and Effort: An Analysis of the Plans Used in the Fifty States, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 15:17)
  Series 169: Seafood Industry
- Seafood Industry, 1975-1979. (Box-folder 15:18-20)
  - Correspondence and reports regarding Virginia seafood industry, 1975-1977., 37 items. (Box-folder 15:18)
    Including copy of 1975 Senate resolution to postpone publication of certain federal shellfish sanitation regulations, 1976-1977 state Marine Resources Commission report, correspondence of Bateman with Governors Mills Godwin and John Dalton and with officials of Virginia Seafood Council regarding promotion of Virginia seafood industry.
    See also Kepone, series 93.
  - Copy of 1977 Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Feasibility Study of a Seafood Industrial Port for Virginia, 1977., 1 item. Copy. (Box-folder 15:19)
  - Correspondence and reports relating to Virginia seafood industry, 1978-1979., 48 items. (Box-folder 15:20)
    Including correspondence between Bateman and officials of City of Newport News and officials of Virginia Seafood Council (VSC), newsletters of VSC, Virginia Institute of Marine Science report on the Virginia oyster industry, and correspondence relating to Newport News Daily Press Reporter's use of Virginia Freedom of Information Act to get access to reports on sanitation in Virginia shellfish processing plants.
  Series 170: Seafood Products Commission
- Seafood Products Commission, 1977-1979. (Box-folder 15:21-22)
  - Correspondence, statistics, and bills, 1977-1979., 74 items. (Box-folder 15:21)
    Regarding work of Virginia Seafood Products Commission and Menhaden licensing. File consists of correspondence with officials of Virginia Seafood Council (VSC), statistics on Menhaden licenses furnished by Marine Resources Commissioner, and materials relating to Bateman's bill (S. 479) for funding of Products Commission.
  - Undated materials relating to Bateman's 1978-1979 bill (S. 479) for the funding of the Seafood Products Commission including copies of bill, substitute, amendments, and background statistics, n.d., 30 items. (Box-folder 15:22)
  Series 171: Sea Grant Consortium
- Letters received by Governor John Dalton regarding proposed Mational Marine Science (Sea Grant) College Consortium, 1979-1980., 6 items. (Box-folder 15:23)
  See also VIMS, series 216.
  Series 172: Seat Belt Legislation
- Letters and enclosed articles received from the American Academy of Pediatrics and the Virginia Farm Bureau Federation, 1981-1982., 14 items. (Box-folder 15:24)
  Endorsing law to require children to wear seatbelts, draft of 1980 seatbelt law and December 1980 study, Children In Crashes.
  See also Child Auto Safety, series 17; and Transportation, series 199-202.
  Series 173: Senate Bills, 1981-1982
- Senate Bills, 1981-1982. (Box-folder 15:25-26)
  - Senate Bills, 1981., 46 items. (Box-folder 15:25)
    Copies of House and Senate bills and resolutions introduced into General Assembly session of January 1981, and copies of several Assembly reports on such matters as the Rehabilitative School Authority, Real Property Management, Bicycle Safety, initiative and referendum, home improvement certification.
  - Senate Bills, 1982., 48 items. (Box-folder 15:26)
    Legislative materials and correspondence relating to progress of several Senate bills in 1982 General Assembly, especially S. 96 (procurement bill), S. 145 (jury sentencing bill), and S. 305 (definitions of Virginia income tax).
    See also Procurement Bill, series 152; and Sentencing, series 177.
  Series 174: Senate Committees
- Lists of committees and subcommittees on which Bateman served, forwarded by the clerk of the Senate, 1968-1982., 5 items. (Box-folder 15:27)
  Series 175: Senate Joint Resolution 24 (S.J.Res. 24)
- Correspondence and copies of regulations pertaining to dormitory visitation policies at Virginia state colleges and universities, 1971-1972., 78 items. (Box-folder 15:28)
  Bateman sponsored 1971 joint resolution expressing the view that "open" visitation violated the moral sense of Virginians. File consists of some correspondence and the visitation rules and regulations of all Virginia schools, especially the College of William and Mary.
  See also Higher Education, series 69; and William and Mary, the College of, series 232.
  Series 176: Senate Rules
- Correspondence and memoranda, regarding Senate rules, 1974-1982., 58 items. (Box-folder 15:29)
  File consists primarily of solicitations by Senators Hunter Andrews and Adelard Brault for comments on Senate rules, Bateman's suggestions (1976, 1977 and 1978), comments on them, and proposed changes in rules by other Senators and by the organization "Common Cause." File also includes several letters (August-September 1976) regarding Bateman's resignation from the Democratic caucus.
  Series 177: Sentencing
- Sentencing, 1949-1982. (Box-folder 16:1-5)
  - Background materials on sentencing, especially jury sentencing, 1949-1972., 10 items. (Box-folder 16:1)
    Including photocopies of 1949 court decision, 1967 article in the Virginia Law Review, American Bar Association standards and briefs from and to the Young Lawyers section of the Virginia Bar Association on indeterminate sentencing.
  - Correspondence, articles, newspaper clippings, and legislative materials related to Bateman's sponsorship of bills to allow judges to sentence in criminal cases, 1973-1977., 20 items. (Box-folder 16:2)
    File includes information pertaining to 1974 bill (S. 176), issues of Judicature and Senate Government and judicial statistics report for 1971-1972.
  - Correspondence, legislative materials, and booklets pertaining to proposed changes in sentencing, 1978-1979., 12 items. (Box-folder 16:3)
    Including 1978 bill for and speech by Attorney General Marshall Coleman on presumptive sentencing, 1978 report on sentencing guidelines, and handwritten and final drafts of Bateman's undated speech (probably 1978) presenting S. 458 for judge sentencing in criminal trials.
  - Legislative materials relating to Bateman's sponsorship of bills for judge sentencing in criminal trials, 1980, 1982., 47 items. (Box-folder 16:4)
    File includes copies of bills and substitutes, 1980 report of joint committee studying sentencing and same documents compiled for use in 1982.
  - Correspondence, legislative materials, and undated background materials relating to Bateman's sponsorship of 1982 bill for judge sentencing in criminal cases, including copies of S. 145 and substitutes and Bateman's 10 March 1982 memorandum to the House of Delegates, 1982., 24 items. (Box-folder 16:5)
  Series 178: Service Life Extension Program
- Bateman's Senate Joint Resolution 181 (S.J.Res. 181), 1979., 47 items. (Box-folder 16:6)
  Resolution memorializes Congress to award Navy's Service Life Extension Program (SLEP) to Newport News Shipbuilding, letters sent (as a result of joint resolution) to Virginia's congressional delegation, correspondence between Bateman and Newport News Shipyard officials and with members of U.S. House and Senate Armed Forces Committee members, including such figures as Senators Barry Goldwater and John Tower.
  Series 179: Sexual Assault
- Sexual Assault, 1977-1980. (Box-folder 16:7-11)
  - Background materials, memoranda, and reports regarding criminal sexual assault bill, 1977-1978., 59 items. (Box-folder 16:7)
    Including statistics, questionnaire, transcripts of testimony, constituent correspondence, and Bateman's (form letter) reply, and copies of bill (S. 291).
  - Memoranda and reports, November-December 1977 by University of Virginia law students on criminal sexual assault forwarded to Bateman in February 1978, 1977-1978., 8 items. (Box-folder 16:8)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, reports and legislative material regarding proposed legislation for criminal sexual assault, 1978-1979., 22 items. (Box-folder 16:9)
    Including interim report of advisory task force (February 1978), critiques of S. 291, and 1979 substitutes for S. 291.
  - Legislative material and reports on proposed criminal sexual assault bills, 1980., 29 items. (Box-folder 16:10)
    Including several copies of competing bills, statements oh and comparisons of them, and analysis by Virginia State Criminal Commission Task Force.
  - Legislative materials and reports on criminal sexual assault bills, 1980., 10 items. (Box-folder 16:11)
    Including comparisons of rival bills, substitutes for one bill (S. 258), and position paper by University of Virginia Law School.
  Series 180: Sex Education
- Sex Education, 1972-1977. (Box-folder 16:12-15)
  - Books and memoranda on sex education in the schools, 1972-1975., 4 items. (Box-folder 16:12)
  - Materials relating to sex education curriculum in Newport News Public Schools, 1976-1977., 22 items. (Box-folder 16:13)
    including minutes of school board meetings, proposed revisions in curriculum, copies of the curriculum, and other information furnished by the school superintendent, and a 1976 Heritage Foundation pamphlet, Secular Humanism and the Schools.
  - Report of the Virginia Advisory Legislative Council on Health Education in the public schools, 1977., 1 item. (Box-folder 16:14)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports relating to sex education in Newport News public schools, 1977., 50 items. (Box-folder 16:15)
    Including letters from constituents, updated curriculum and a citizen's committee Report to the People.
  Series 181: Soft Drink Tax
- Correspondence and legislative materials related to proposed tax on soft drinks, sponsored in 1977 by Senator Madison Marye, and in 1980 by Bateman, 1977, 1980., 9 items. (Box-folder 16:16)
  Series 182: Southern Legislative Conference
- Announcement, agenda, and registration information for 1982 annual meeting of the Southern Legislative Conference of the Council of State Governments, 1982., 5 items. (Box-folder 16:17)
  Series 183: Special Education
- Correspondence, bulletins, and reports, 1972-1974., 23 items. (Box-folder 16:18)
  Regarding Virginia's programs for the blind, retarded and handicapped, including 1972 report of the Virginia Commission for the Visually Handicapped, and Bateman's 1974 correspondence with constituents urging increased funding for special education.
  Series 184: Spending Limit Proposal
- Draft "Fair Tax Amendment" forwarded to Bateman by State Senator Elliot Schewel, 1980., 2 items. (Box-folder 16:19)
  Series 185: Spouse Abuse
- Correspondence and proposed bill, urging the creation of a "Family Trust Fund" to provide financial assistance to abused spouses and children, 1982., 2 items. (Box-folder 16:20)
  Series 186: State Water Control Board (SWCB)
- State Water Control Board (SWCB) (Box-folder 16:21-23)
  - Study, Virginia Water Law: An Economic Appraisal, presented to State Water Control Board, January 1976., 1 item. (Box-folder 16:21)
  - Memoranda relating to SWCB study of Water Resource Law and policy, 1976., 13 items. (Box-folder 16:22)
    File contains status report and 9 attachments which summarize water law proposals, plan of action, minutes from meetings, and comments on proposals.
    See also Water Resources, series 222-224; Water Study of Virginia and North Carolina, and other files under "Water."
  - Correspondence from York County, Virginia County Administrator (1978), and from SWCB member (1979) regarding the Hampton Roads Sanitary District, 1978-1979., 3 items. (Box-folder 16:23)
  Series 187: Taxation
- Taxation, 1971-1981 (Box 16-17)
  - Miscellaneous background materials on taxation policy in Virginia, 1971-1974., 25 items. (Box-folder 16:24)
    Including 1971 booklet on local tax rates, 1973 bill for exemptions from retail tax, 1973 booklet on state and local taxes in the South, several January 1974 proposed amendments to tax laws by Bateman, and two copies of Volume I of 1974 report on Reforming the Virginia Property Tax.
  - Volume II of 1974 report, Reforming the Virginia Property Tax, 2 items. (Box-folder 16:25)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports concerning taxation in Virginia, 1974-1976., 19 items. (Box-folder 16:26)
    Including digest of 1974 bills affecting taxation, correspondence between Bateman and State Tax Commissioner William H. Forst, 1974 Tayloe Murphy Institute Report on Virginia's Real Property Tax, and Department of Taxation 1976 reports on Virginia assessment/sales ratio and 1976 legislative digest.
  - Background information on taxation in Virginia, 1975-1981., 13 items. (Box-folder 17:1)
    Including 1975-1976 annual report of Department of Taxation, copies of two 1978 statements on taxation issues by Governor John Dalton, 1978 Department of Taxation legislative digest copy of 1980 tax "set-off" bill, and 1981 presentation to Senate Finance Committee on Virginia's Capital Tax.
  Series 188: Taxation Procedures
- Taxation Procedures, 1979-1982. (Box-folder 17:2-4)
  - Memoranda and other materials related to work of study committee on the practices and procedures in the collection and administration of state taxes, 1979., 9 items. (Box-folder 17:2)
    Including copies of authorizing resolution and membership list, report of state tax law revision task force and initial staff report on practices and procedures of collection.
  - Memoranda and other items relating to work of committee studying tax collection procedures, 1979., 19 items. (Box-folder 17:3)
    Including minutes of meetings, Department of Taxation's response to task force report, memorandum comparing task force and Department of Taxation positions, and copy of relevant court decision.
  - Materials relating to work of committee studying tax collection procedures, 1979-1982., 12 items. (Box-folder 17:4)
    Including draft legislation, two drafts of committee reports (1980), Bateman's "concurring statement," Bateman's handwritten notes from unspecified meeting, and other correspondence regarding tax collection, 1980 and 1982.
  Series 189: Taxation Expenditures
- Memoranda and reports related to study of tax expenditures, 1980-1981., 5 items. (Box-folder 17:5)
  Including studies of tax expenditures in Maryland, California, and Wisconsin.
  Series 190: Taxation of Corporate Income
- Materials relating to the Emergency Tax Recovery Act of 1982 (S. 69), 1982., 21 items. (Box-folder 17:6)
  Including copies of substitute for bill, voting tally sheet, analysis of bill, and copies of tax forms.
  Series 191: Tax Relief for the Elderly
- (Box-folder 17:7-9)
  - Memoranda, correspondence, and legislative materials relating to tax relief for the elderly, 1971-1973., 35 items. (Box-folder 17:7)